Guide to the Raisa Berg Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: Works and Writings by R.Berg; Research Data and Notes, 1937-2006
  - Subseries II.5: Fragments, extracts, notes, and loose pages from various unidentified works, various dates
    - Fragments, extracts, notes, and loose pages from various unidentified works, various dates (Box 50, Folder 11 to 22)
- Series III: Human Rights Activity, 1975-1990s
  This series contains Raisa Berg's letters to political leaders, newsletters, leaflets and press on dissidents and refuseniks, materials of campaign for Mikhail Meilakh defense. More materials on R. Berg's human rights activity are parts of other series of the collection.
  - Letters to political leaders (Leonid Brezhnev, George Bush, Anatolii Dobrynin, Mikhail Gorbachev, Queen Elizabeth II, Ronald Reagan), 1977-1991 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, 1975-1986 (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Leaflets and press on dissidents and refuseniks (see also Series VI: Research and Reference Materials--Subseries VI.2: Printed materials) (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - Ginzburg, Aleksandr, 1997 (Box 51, Folder 3-A)
    Materials of campaign for his defense in regard to the situation in Russkaia mysl': letters of various people, newspaper clippings
  - Makarenko, Mikhail: see Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Makarenko (Box 11, Folders 11-12)
    - Autobiographical note
    - Publications about him
    - His writings
    - Memento: Society for the Research of Problems of Culutre and Man Under Totalitarianism
  - Meilakh, Mikhail (materials of campaign for his defense. His correspondence with R.Berg see in Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Meilakh: Box 13, Folder 8) (Box 51, Folder 4 to 14)
    - Letters of various people, 1983-1987 (Box 51, Folder 4 to 7)
    - Articles and essays by R.Berg
      - "Govorit stolitsa khamskogo khanstva" (Box 51, Folder 8)
      - "This is the capital of the Caddish Khanate speaking" (Box 51, Folder 9)
      - "Why Mikhail Meilakh has been sentenced to seven years of labor camps and five years of internal exile" (Box 51, Folder 10)
      - "Za chto Mikhail Meilakh osuzhden na 7 let lagerei i 5 let ssylki" (Box 51, Folder 11)
      - Fragments from R.Berg's memoirs related to M.Meilakh (Box 51, Folder 12)
      - Clippings, press, varia, 1983-1986 (Box 51, Folder 13 to 14)
  - Neifakh, Aleksandr A.: see Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Neifakh (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "Russian geneticist looks at human rights", 1989 (audiotape): see Series V--Audiomaterials (Box 57, Folder 23)
- Series IV: Personal Documents and Biographical Materials, 1939-2003
  Contains certificates, educational and financial documents, IDs, immigration and travel documents of Raisa Berg. Biographical materials include autobiographies, CVs, bibliography of Berg's works, interviews with her, articles about her, materials on emigration of Raisa Berg's daughter Maria Shenderova; address books, business cards, calendars, exhibit catalogs, playbills, and other related materials.
  - Personal Documents:
    - Awards, 1990-1997 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Birth certificate, divorce certificate, retirement ID, employment history, 1974 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Educational Diplomas and Certificates, 1939-1965 (Box 52, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Financial Documents, 1970s-1990s (Box 52, Folder 5 to 6)
    - IDs, 1975-1999 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Immigration and travel documents, 1974-1990s (Box 52, Folder 8 to 9)
    - Legal, 1994-2003 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Memberships, 1980s-1990s (Box 52, Folder 11 to 12)
    - Passports, 1981 1986 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Subscriptions, 1979-1994 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Varia, 1970s-1990s (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - Biographical Materials:
    - Autobiography and biographical notes, undated (Box 52, Folder 16 to 20)
    - R.Berg - painter:
      - "Autobigraphy of self-educated painter", undated (Box 53, Folder 1)
      - "Ia - abstraktsionist vosemnadtsatogo veka", undated, 1982 (Box 53, Folder 2)
      - "Vremia moe nastalo", 1983 (Box 53, Folder 3)
      - Exhibits: catalogs, invitations, lists of pictures, various years (Box 53, Folder 4)
      - Petition, undated (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - CV, various years (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - List of publications, various years (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - Interviews, 1960s-1993 (videotape with R.Berg's interview of 2002: see Series V--Videomaterials--Box 57, Folder 23) (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - Emigration of Raisa Berg's daughter Maria Shenderova (documents, letters, essays) (Box 53, Folder 9 to 11)
    - Articles about her in newspapers, 1975-1984 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - About her: to 90th anniversary, 2003 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Obituaries, 2006 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified. "Izbergizm na tezoimenitstvo vseslavneishei Raisy L'vovny Berg", undated (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - Contacts (address book, business cards, addresses and telephones of various people and organizations), various dates (Box 54, Folder 1 to 4)
    - List of addressees, calendars, various dates (Box 54, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Inscriptions to various people, 1990 (Box 54, Folder 7)
    - Invitations to exhibit openings of various artists, 1970s-1980s (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Catalogs of exhibits of various artists, 1960s-1980s (some with inscriptions) (Box 54, Folder 9 to 10)
    - Playbills, programs, tickets, 1970s-1980s (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Varia, undated (Box 54, Folder 12)
- Series V: Photographs, Art Works, and Video-Audio Materials, 1898-2000s
  Photographs and slides of various people including many prominent figures, such as Iosif Brodskii, Vadim Delone, Evgenii Shvarts, Anton Chekhov, Maksim Gorky, Lev Berg, Sergei Chetverikov, Vladimir Efroimson, Andrei Sakharov, Ivan Shmal'gauzen, Viktor Sosnora, Nikolai Timofeev-Resovskii, Galina Starovoitova, Iosif and Leon Orbeli, and many noted scholars. Photographs arranged alphabetically. Unidentified photographs, photos of faculty members of the Department of Darwinism, and family photographs stored at the end.
  This series also includes original prints, negatives, and slides of Raisa Berg's graphic works and pictures. There are also video- and audiotapes with her interviews.
  - Photographs and Slides:
    - Adams, Mark, undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Aleksandrov, Aleksandr Danilovich, Leningrad, 1966 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - Aleksandrova, Marianna Leonidovna, Akademgorodok, 1967 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Alekseev, Vasilii Mikhailovich, Borovoe, 1941 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - Alekseeva, Liudmila: see Family photos
    - Andriianov, A.P.: see Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1950
    - Ashkenazi, E.K., 1947 (with inscription) (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - Ashkenazi, Konstantin Mironovich, 1955 undated (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - Astaurov, Boris L'vovich, undated (Box 55, Folder 6)
    - Bazumov: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Beliaev, D.K.: see Gandhi
    - Beling, Adelaida Maksimovna (aka Belina), 1987 undated (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Berg, Lev Semenovich, various places, 1899-1950 (Box 55, Folder 8 to 12)
    - Berg, Raisa, various places, 1929-2005 (See also: Aleksandrova; Ashkenazi; Berg, Lev; Borodkin; Giliarov; Golubovskii; Iurenev; Kerkis; Keshman; Kiknadze; Likhachev; Petrochenkov; Tukerman; Volobuev; Wolf; Zakharov; Zhazhoian; Kafedra Darvinizma; Family photos) (Box 55, Folder 13 to 21)
    - Binevich, 1982 2001 (2 photos) (Box 55, Folder 22)
    - Borodkin, Paris, 2005 (Box 55, Folder 23)
    - Bridges, K., Leningrad, 1933-1934 (Box 55, Folder 24)
    - Brink, Janny M., van, Utrecht, 1980 (Box 55, Folder 25)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, 1942-1963 (Box 55, Folder 26)
    - Chekhov, Anton Pavlovich, undated (Box 55, Folder 27)
    - Chetverikov, Sergei Sergeevich, Moscow, 1929 (Box 55, Folder 28)
    - Cliburn, Van, undated (Box 55, Folder 29)
    - Crow, James F., Japan, 1981 (Box 55, Folder 30)
    - Delone, Vadim, undated (Box 55, Folder 31)
    - Demech-Marcaillou, Elena, St. Petersburg, 2001 (Box 55, Folder 32)
    - Demin, L.A.: see Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1947
    - Deriugin, Konstantin Mikhailovich, [1930] (Box 55, Folder 33)
    - Deiugina, Nadezhda Mikhailovna, [1930] (Box 55, Folder 33)
    - Dudanova, Inna: see Golubovskii
    - Efroimson, Vladimir Pavlovich, 1959 undated (Box 55, Folder 34)
    - Egiaian, Gregor, undated (Box 55, Folder 35)
    - Epel'man, Galina and Grigorii, Norfolk, 1977 1982 (Box 55, Folder 36)
    - Filatov, Dmitrii Petrovich, Moscow, 1942 (with inscription) (Box 55, Folder 37)
    - Fortunatov, Mikhail Alekseevich, 1952-1954 (with inscription) (Box 55, Folder 38)
    - Gandhi, Indira, New Delhi, 1983 (Box 55, Folder 39)
    - Giliarov, Merkurii Sergeevich, Moscow, 1968 (Box 55, Folder 40)
    - Gimel'farb, A., 1977 (with inscription) (Box 55, Folder 41)
    - Ginzburg, Aleksandr, Moscow, 1959 (photocopy) (Box 55, Folder 42)
    - Golenopol'skii, Tankred Grigor'evich, Moscow, 1960s (clipping) (Box 55, Folder 43)
    - Golubovskii, Mikhail Davidovich, various places, 1970s-1980s (including family photographs) (Box 55, Folder 44)
    - Gorky, Maksim: see Chekhov
    - Gorobets: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Grasgof: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Grosman, Alik, 1968 1977 (Box 55, Folder 45)
    - Grosman, Evgenii, Chicago, 1988 (Box 55, Folder 46)
    - Gusev, Vladimir A. and family, 1970s (with inscriptions) (Box 56, Folder 1)
    - Holmes Family: see Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Holmes (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Ignatov, Pavel Grigor'evich, 1898-1900s (copies) (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - Iurenev, Sergei Nikolaevich, Bukhara, 1967 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - Ivanov, Iurii Nikolaevich, Akademgorodok, 1967 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - Kaidanov, Leonid Zinov'evich: see Golubovskii
    - Kalinin, Oleg Mikhailovich, Leningrad, 1967 (with inscription. See also: Likhachev) (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - Karpov, S.D., 2002 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Karpova, Tatiana, 2002 (see also: Berg, Raisa, undated; Keshman) (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Karpovskaia, Elena: see Golubovskii
    - Kerkis, Iulii Iakovlevich, 1960s-1970s (see also: Vavilov) (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - Keshman, Elena, 1980-1992 (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - Khao: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Khod'khov, Leontii Evmenovich: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Kiknadze, Iia Ivanovna, Novosibirsk, 1967 (Box 56, Folder 9)
    - Kirpichnikova, Elizaveta: see Family photos
    - Kolosova, Liudmila, Novosibirsk, 1980s (Box 56, Folder 10)
    - Kol'tsov, Nikolai Konstantinovich, Moscow, 1930s (Box 56, Folder 11)
    - Kontsevaia-Kol'man, Ekaterina, Stockholm, 1983 (Box 56, Folder 12)
    - Kosovskaia, Esfir' Borisovna, uhndated (Box 56, Folder 13)
    - Krasnovidova, S: see Kafedra Darvinizma
    - Kryshova, Nina Andreevna, Leningrad, 1960s (Box 56, Folder 14)
    - Krzhizhanovskii, Gleb Maksimil'ianovich, Borovoe, 1942 (from E.Zernova's drawing) (Box 56, Folder 15)
    - Kulakov, Mikhail, 1977 (Box 56, Folder 16)
    - Levitskii, Grigorii Andreevich, Leningrad, 1932 (Box 56, Folder 17)
    - Likhachev, Ivan Alekseevich, Leningrad, Vladivostok, 1963 1966 (Box 56, Folder 18)
    - Lindberg, G.U.: see Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1950
    - Litinskii, Vadim: see Berg, Raisa, undated
    - Liubishchev, A.A.,, 1965-1971 (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 19)
    - Lobashov, Mikhail: see Berg, Raisa, 1931
    - Logsdon, Patricia: see Zaidman, Anna
    - Lus, L.L.: see Bridges, K.; Prokof'eva-Bergol'govskaia
    - Lusis, Ianis Ianovich, Riga, 1977-1978 undated (Box 56, Folder 20)
    - McCarthy, Ruby "Tess": see Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--McCarthy (Box 11, Folders 8-9)
    - Makarenko, Mikhail, 1980 with inscription (Box 56, Folder 21)
    - Malakhovskaia, Natal'ia, 1985 (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 22)
    - Maletskaia, Ekaterina: see Berg, Raisa, 1967
    - Maletskii, Stanislav Ignat'evich, Novosibirsk, 1980s (Box 56, Folder 23)
    - Malinovskii, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich, 1940s-1995 (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 24)
    - Mazing, Roza Andreevna, Leningrad, 1930s (Box 56, Folder 25)
    - Marcaillou, Michel, St. Petersburg, 2001: see Demech-Marcaillou
    - Medvedev, Nikolai Nikolaevich, Leningrad, 1932 (Box 56, Folder 26)
    - Medvedev, Zhores, undated (Box 56, Folder 27)
    - Mekler, Iurii: see Berg, Raisa, 1983
    - Meller, German, 1927 (Box 56, Folder 28)
    - Mitrofanov, 1968 (Box 56, Folder 29)
    - Morgan, T.: see Vavilov
    - Murzaev, E.M.: see Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1947
    - Nabokov, V.V., undated (Box 56, Folder 30)
    - Neiding, Veronika, Moscow, 1970s-1980s (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 31)
    - Neifakh, Aleksandr A., undated (Box 56, Folder 32)
    - Nikoro, Zoia Sofron'evna, 1960s-1970s (see also: Golubovskii) (Box 56, Folder 33)
    - Novikov, Ivan Ivanovich: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Orbeli, Iosif Obgarovich, Komarovo, 1950s (Box 56, Folder 34)
    - Orbeli, Leon Obgarovich, Kaltushi, Komarovo, 1950s (Box 56, Folder 34)
    - Panov, Evgenii: see Golubovskii
    - Petrochenkov, Valerii, undated (Box 56, Folder 35)
    - Plus, Nadine, Moscow, Leningrad, 1977 1978 (see also: Golubovskii; Nikoro) (Box 56, Folder 36)
    - Pomerantseva, Marina Dmitrievna, Iurmala, 1988 (Box 56, Folder 37)
    - Prokof'eva-Bergol'govskaia, Aleksandra Alekseevna, 1932 undated (see also: Vavilov) (Box 56, Folder 38)
    - Ratsek, V.I.: see Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1947
    - Rautian, undated (Box 56, Folder 39)
    - Razumov: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Reformatskaia, Nadezhda Vasil'evna: see Berg, Raisa, 1956
    - Regel', Elena Dmitrievna: see Beling, Adelaida Maksimovna
    - Rubashkin: see Golubovskii
    - Sakharov, Andrei Dmitrievich, 1974 undated (negative and print) (Box 56, Folder 40)
    - Sakharov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1957 (with inscription. See also: Timofeev-Resovskii) (Box 56, Folder 41)
    - Serebrovskii, Aleksandr Sergeevich, Moscow, 1940s (copy) (Box 56, Folder 42)
    - Shao Qiquan: see Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Shao Qiquan (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Shenderova, Mariia: see Plus; Family photos
    - Shmal'gauzen, Ivan Ivanovich, Moscow, 1950s (Box 56, Folder 43)
    - Shvarts, Evgenii L'vovich, undated (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 44)
    - Solzhenitsin, Aleksandr Isaevich, 1966 or 1967 (Box 56, Folder 45)
    - Sosnora, Viktor, 1964 (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 46)
    - Starovoitova, Galina: see Sakharov, Andrei Dmitrievich
    - Stein, Hilde, 1984 (with inscription) (Box 56, Folder 47)
    - Svetovidov, A.N.: see Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1950
    - Teilhard de Chardin, Pierre, undated (Box 56, Folder 48)
    - Temin, Howard, undated (Box 56, Folder 49)
    - Timofeev-Resovskii, Nikolai Vladimirovich, 1960s undated (see also: Vavilov) (Box 56, Folder 50)
    - Timofeeva-Resovskaia, E.A.: see Berg, Raisa, 1956
    - Tukerman, L.A., 1959 (Box 56, Folder 51)
    - Vavilov, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1930s (Box 56, Folder 52)
    - Vernadskii, Vladimir Ivanovich, Borovoe, 1942 (copy) (Box 56, Folder 53)
    - Volobuev, Vitalii, 1999 (Box 56, Folder 54)
    - Volodin, undated (Box 56, Folder 55)
    - Voronin, Slava: see Ivanov, Iurii
    - Vorontsov, Nikolai N., 1960s-1990s (Box 56, Folder 56)
    - Wolf family, 1975-1978 (Box 56, Folder 57)
    - Zaidman, Anna, St.Louis, 1990 (Box 56, Folder 58)
    - Zakharov, 1972 (Box 56, Folder 59)
    - Zavadskii, Kirill Mikhailovich: see Kafedra Darvinizma LGU
    - Zhazhoian, Manuk, Paris, 1996 (Box 56, Folder 60)
    - Zhukoborskii, Savelii (aka Savva, Savelii L.), 1974-1982 undated (with inscriptions) (Box 56, Folder 61)
    - Zinner, Ervin, 1962 (Box 56, Folder 62)
    - Unidentified (Box 56, Folder 63)
    - Kafedra Darvinizma LGU, 1958 (Box 56, Folder 64)
    - Family photographs, 1953-2000s (see also: Berg, Lev) (Box 56, Folder 65)
    - Various:
      - City views and other: Leningrad, Tomsk, Kurily (see also: Leningrad, 1933-1934 in Bridges, K.) (Box 57, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Exhibition Sovest' 1988 (Box 57, Folder 3)
      - Related materials (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Art works, various years (prints, negatives, and slides) (Box 57, Folder 5 to 22)
  - Videotapes
    - Interview with R.Berg, 2002 (Box 57, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified (Box 57, Folder 23)
  - Audiocassette
    - "Politicizing of science in the Soviet Union" - radioprogram with R.Berg in Dangers of apathy, undated (Box 57, Folder 23)
    - "Russian geneticist looks at human rights", 1989 (Box 57, Folder 23)
- Series VI: Research and Reference Materials, 1919-2004
  The series comprises writings by various authors, printed materials, and various research and reference materials. Organized in three subseries.
  - Subseries VI.1: Writings by Others, 1919-2003
    Articles on scientific subjects and history of science. Reprints, off-prints, typescripts (many with authors' inscriptions). Organized alphabetically by authors. Also contains programs and publications of various conferences (stored at the end of the subseries). Writings on general subjects, literature, etc. are parts of other series of the collection; references are provided.
    - Various authors:
      - Abdo, S.: see Schwab, M.
      - Abrahamson, S., 1956 (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Ackermann, Mary: see Sokoloff, Alexander
      - Adams, Mark B., 1968-1989 (with author's inscription) (Box 58, Folder 2 to 5)
      - Adelberg, E. A.: see Demerec, Milislav
      - Agadzhanian, A.K.: see Vorontsov, N.N.
      - Ahearn, J. N.: see Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Ahrens, H.: see Bellman, K.
      - Ahuja, M. R., 1978 (see also: Schwab, M.) (Box 58, Folder 6)
      - Akhverdian, M.R.: see Liapunova, E.A.
      - Aleksandrov, Igor' Donatovich, 1991 (see also: Maluta, S. S.) (Box 58, Folder 7)
      - Aleksandrov, Iu.N., 1969-1970 (see also: Gershenzon, Sergei Mikhailovich) (Box 58, Folder 7)
      - Aleksandrov, V.Ia. "Trudnye gody sovetskoi biologii: iz zapisok sovremennika", with author's inscription (clippings from Znanie-Sila): see Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Aleksandrov, V.Ia.: Box 1, Folder 6) (Box 58, Folder 7)
      - Aleksandrova, V. D.: see Mazing, V.V.
      - Alekseev, V. P.,1967-1970 (Box 58, Folder 8)
      - Allakhverdiev, Kh. M: see Alpatov, V. V.
      - Alpatov V.V., 1935-1977 (Box 58, Folder 9 to 10)
      - Altukhov, IU. P., 1969-1990 (with author's inscription) (Box 58, Folder 11)
      - Amosova, I.S.: see Kaidanov, Leonid Z.
      - Anders, Annerose: see Anders, Fritz; Schwab, M.
      - Anders, Fritz,, 1979-1986 (see also: Ahuja, M. R.; Kuhn, Claudia; Schwab, M.) (Box 58, Folder 12)
      - Anderson, Paul K.: see Dunn, L. C.
      - Anderson, Wyatt W.: see Ayala, F. J.; Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Aniskin, V.M.: see Volobuev, V.T.
      - Artavanis-Tsakonas, Spyros: see Fortini, Mark E.
      - Aoki, Kenichi, 1981 (Box 58, Folder 13)
      - Arber, Werner, 1984 (Box 58, Folder 14)
      - Arens, Marie-Francoise: see David, Jean
      - Armstrong, Robert A., 1976 (Box 58, Folder 14)
      - Aronova, Elena A., 1971-2002 (Box 58, Folder 15)
      - Astaurov, B.L., 1957 (with author's inscription) (Box 58, Folder 16)
      - Aula, Perti: see Nichols, Warren W.
      - Autrum, Hansjochem, 1983-1988 (Box 58, Folder 17)
      - Ayala, Francisco J., 1966-1973 (Box 58, Folder 18)
      - Babkov, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1972-1989 with author's inscription (see also: "Between Science and Poetry: Velimir Khlebnikov's 'Metabiosis'" (typescript) and an article in Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Babkov: Box 2, Folders 1-7) (Box 59, Folder 1)
      - Baev, A.A.: see Beliaev, D. K.
      - Balanovskaia, E. V., 1990 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - Balbinder, E.: see Demerec, Milislav
      - Baranov, O.K.: see Vorontsov, N.N.
      - Barbakar, Nikolai I.: see Gerasimova, Tatiana I.
      - Barnekow, Angelika: see Anders, Fritz
      - Barr, A.R.: see Iltis, W.G.; Yen, J.H.
      - Batsuur', Zh.: see Balanovskaia, E. V.
      - Beasley, Andrew B.: see Dunn, L. C.
      - Bech, K., 1961 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - Beckendorf, Steven K.: see McGinnis, William
      - Bei-Bienko, G. Ia., 1967 (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - Beklemishev, V. N., 1964 (Box 59, Folder 4)
      - Beliaev, D. K., 1963-1987 (see also Korochkin, L.I.) (Box 59, Folder 5)
      - Beliaeva, E.S.: see Kaidanov, Leonid Z.
      - Beliaeva, V. N.: see Dubinin, N. P.
      - Belkovskii, Andrei N.: see Balanovskaia, E. V. and Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Belkovskii (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Bellman, K., von, 1965-1966 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 6)
      - Bemis, William E.: see Birshtein, Vadim
      - Bennett, Dorothea, 1961-1964 (see also: Dunn, L.C.) (Box 59, Folder 7)
      - Bennett, Frederick D.: see Brown, Spencer W.
      - Beregovoi, V. E., 1972-1977 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 8)
      - Berg, Clair M.: see Berg, Douglas E.
      - Berg, Douglas E., 1982-1985 (Box 59, Folder 9)
      - Berg, Lev Semenovich, 1949 (Box 59, Folder 10)
      - Berg, Maria: see Boyd, A. E.
      - Berman, D. I., 1970 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 11)
      - Berry, H. K.: see Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Bertalanffy, Ludwig, von, undated (Box 59, Folder 12)
      - Bessmertnaya, S. Ia.: see Dubinin, N. P.
      - Beyth, Y.: see Dudakov, E.
      - Bialojan, Siegfried: see Renkawitz-Pohl, Renate
      - Biel, Susan W.: see Berg, Douglas E.
      - Biggart, John, 1982 (Box 59, Folder 12)
      - Bingham, Paul M., 1982 (with R.Berg's notes. See also Kidwell, Margaret G.) (Box 59, Folder 13)
      - Birshtein, Vadim J., 1980s (see also Series I: Correspondence--Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals--Birshtein: Box 3, Folder 1) (Box 59, Folder 14)
      - Black, G. A.: see Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Blaikher, Leonid, 1968-1972 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 15)
      - Blair, James E.: see Spitsberg, Vitaly L.
      - Blober, Gunter: see Chung Nan Chang
      - Bodmer, Walter F.: see Sved, J.A.
      - Boesiger, B.: see Boesiger, Ernest
      - Boesiger, Ernest, 1968-1974 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 16)
      - Boeskorov, G.G.: see Vorontsov, N.N.
      - Bogdanov, Iu, 1992 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 17)
      - Bogomolova, V. I., 1973 (Box 59, Folder 17)
      - Boldyreva, L., undated (Box 59, Folder 18)
      - Bol'shakov, V.N.: see Kaidanov, Leonid Z.
      - Bondareva, A.A., 1979 (see also Mosolov, A.N.) (Box 59, Folder 19)
      - Borkhsenius, O.N.: see Osipov, D.V.
      - Born, H.J.: see Gerlach, J.; Wolf, P.M.
      - Bouletreau, Michel, 1971-1972 (Box 59, Folder 19)
      - Bowman, Lewis H., 1983 (Box 59, Folder 19)
      - Boyd, A. E., III, 1986 (Box 59, Folder 19)
      - Bregliano, Jean-Claude: see Picard, Georges
      - Brewster, Weldon: see Patterson, J.T.
      - Britten, Roy J., undated (Box 59, Folder 20)
      - Brown, Byron: see Clewell, Don B.
      - Brown, Spencer W., 1957-1963 (Box 59, Folder 21)
      - Bucheton, Alain, 1986 (see also Picard, Georges) (Box 59, Folder 22)
      - Budyko, M. I., 1995 (Box 59, Folder 22)
      - Bull, James J., 1978-1980 (with author's inscription) (Box 59, Folder 23)
      - Burla, H.: see Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Carle, George F.: see Berg, Douglas E.
      - Carlson, Elof A., 1966 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      - Caron, Laurent A.: see Fortini, Mark E.
      - Carron, Richard L.: see Clewell, Don B.
      - Carson, Hampton L., 1967-1973 (see also: Dobzhansky, T.; Ikeda, Hiroshi) (Box 60, Folder 2)
      - Cartler, S. M.: see Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Carvalcho, G.G.: see Malogolowkin, Chana
      - Castaneda, H.C.: see Hoenigsberg, H.F.
      - Cavalcanti, A. G. L.: see Dobzhansky, Theodosius
      - Celerier, Marie-Louise: see Thomas-Orillard, Michele